[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐]
赋值、状态和副作用
Assignment, State, and Side-effects
教授：到目前为止 我们编写程序
PROFESSOR: Well, so far we've invented enough programming
做了一些非常复杂事情
to do some very complicated things.
并且关于编程你们确实已经学到了很多
And you surely learned a lot about programming at this point.
你们已经学习了几乎所有的
You've learned almost all the most important tricks
那些拥有大量经验的人才能领悟的技巧
that usually don't get taught to people until they have had a lot of experience.
例如，数据导向编程是一个主要的技巧
For example, data directed programming is a major trick,
昨天你们也看到了一种解释型语言
and yesterday you also saw an interpreted language.
我们所做的这一切
We did this all in a computer language,
目前来讲
at this point,
都是在一种没有赋值语句的计算机语言中完成的
where there was no assignment statement.
想必 对于你们中已经见过
And presumably, for those of you who've
Basic或者Pascal或者其他什么语言的人来说
seen your Basic or Pascal or whatever,
也许，赋值语句被认为是最重要的东西
that's usually considered the most important thing.
今天我们将要做一些糟糕的事情
Well today, we're going to do something horrible.
我们要把赋值语句加进来
We're going to add an assignment statement.
既然在没有赋值语句的时候，我们都可以很好地完成工作
And since we can do all these wonderful things without it,
为什么我们还要把它加进来呢？
why should we add it?
我们需要认识到一件重要的事情
An important thing to understand is
首先，我们要
that today we're going to
定下一个原则
first of all, have a rule,
而我们将一直遵守这个规则
which is going to always be obeyed,
我们为语言引入新的特性的唯一原因
which is the only reason we ever add a feature to our language
是因为有一个好的理由
is because there is a good reason.
这个好理由就是能力
And the good reason is going to boil down to the ability,
现在你获得了
you now get an ability
把问题分解为不同的小部分
to break a problem into pieces that are different sets of pieces
在过去你可能在不使用这种能力的情况下分解问题
then you could have broken it down without that,
从而领悟解耦的另一种含义
give you another means of decomposition.
我们这就开始
However, let's just start.
我们从回顾我们的
Let me quick begin by reviewing
现在已经有的这种语言出发
the kind of language that we have now.
我们之前写的是所谓的函数式程序
We've been writing what's called functional programs.
函数式程序
And functional programs
是一种对数学真理的编码
are a kind of encoding of mathematical truths.
例如，当我们看到
For example, when we look at
像幻灯片上这样阶乘过程时
the factorial procedure that you see on the slide here,
基本上是两个子句
it's basically two clauses.
如果n是1，则结果是1
If n is one, the result is one,
否则返回n乘以n-1的阶乘
otherwise n times factorial n minus one.
这是n的阶乘
That's factorial of n.
它就是n的阶乘
Well, that is factorial of n.
如果用一些其他的
And written down in some other obscure notation
那些你在微积分课堂上学到的晦涩的符号来写
that you might have learned in calculus classes,
以数学上的逻辑来写
mathematical logic,
如果n等于1
what you see there is if n equals one,
那么n的阶乘结果是1，否则，
for the result of n factorial is one, otherwise,
如果n大于1，则n的阶乘就是n乘以n-1的阶乘
greater than one, n factorial is n times n minus one factorial.
#TBD
True statements,
这就是我们一直以来用的那种语言
that's the kind of language we've been using.
#TBD
And whenever we have true statements of that sort,
有一种理解它们是如何工作的方法
there is a kind of, a way of understanding how they work
就是这些过程可以由代换演变出来
which is that such processes can be evolved by substitution.
来看第二张幻灯片
And so we see on the second slide here,
我们理解执行的过程
that the way we understand the execution implied
隐含在表达式的顺序中
by those statements in arranged in that order,
就是你在过程体中连续地将形式参数，代换为实际参数的顺序
is that you do successive substitutions of arguments for formal parameters in the body of a procedure.
这是基本上是一系列的等价代换
This is basically a sequence of equalities.
4的阶乘是4乘以3的阶乘
Factorial four is four times factorial three.
也就是4乘以3乘以2的阶乘
That is four times three times factorial of two
以此类推
and so on.
#TBD
We're always preserving truth.
尽管我们正在讨论#TBD
Even though we're talking about true statements,
这里会有超过一个#TBD
there might be more than one organization of these true statements
来描述一个特定的函数的计算
to describe the computation of a particular function,
这个特定的函数的值的计算
the computation of the value of a particular function.
所以，让我来看下一个例子
So, for example, looking at the next one here.
这有一个计算m与n的和的办法
Here is a way of looking at the sum of n and m.
我们使用一个递归的过程来完成这个任务
And we did this one by a recursive process.
它就是sum的增加，及n与m的减少
It's the increment of the sum of the decrement of n and m.
当然，这里就是一些数学的逻辑，解释了这个方法
And, of course, there is some piece of mathematical logic here that describes that.
就是sum的增加以及n和m的减少
It's the increment of the sum of the decrement of n and m,
跟之前那个一样
just like that.
所以这儿并没有什么特殊的魔法
So there's nothing particularly magic about that.
当然，如果我们可以再来看一个相同的迭代过程
And, of course, if we can also look at an iterative process for the same,
一个对于同样的函数进行逐步迭代的过程的程序
a program that evolves an iterative process, for the same function.
这两个程序将得到同样的结果
These are two things that compute the same answer.
我们就可以认为这两个程序在数学上是等效的
And we have equivalent mathematical truths that are arranged there.
#TBD
And just the way you arrange those truths determine the particular process.
In the way choose and arrange them determines the process that's evolved.
因此我们有讨论两个函数被计算的灵活性
So we have the flexibility of talking about both the function to be computed,
#TBD
and the method by which it's computed.
So it's not clear we need more.
然而，今天我要来讲这个糟糕的东西
However, today I'm going to this awful thing.
我要给大家介绍赋值操作
I'm going to introduce this assignment operation.
这是什么？
Now, what is this?
首先，在编程语言中有另一种语句
Well, first of all, there is going to be another kind of kind of statement, if you will,
这种语句叫做SET！
in a programming language called Set!
它可以用来进行赋值，我在后面加上一个感叹号
Things that do things like assignment, I'm going to put exclamation points after.
我马上就讲这个感叹号是什么意思
We'll talk about what that means in a second.
这个感叹号，与问号类似
The exclamation point, again like question mark,
是我们给名字随意加的符号
is an arbitrary thing we attach to the symbol which is the name,
它对于系统来说没有意义
has no significance to the system.
它唯一的意义就是告诉我们
The only significance is to me and you
注意这里是某种赋值
to alert you that this is an assignment of some sort.
但是我们要给某个变量
But we're going to set a variable
赋一个值
to a value.
这意味着
And what that's going to mean
在某个时间点发生了一些事情
is that there is a time at which something happens.
这是一个时间点
Here's a time.
如果时间以这个方向流动
If I have time going this way,
#TBD
it's a time access.
时间在纸面上由上到下地流逝
Time progresses by walking down the page.
赋值是第一个
Then an assignment is the first thing we have
使过去和未来之间产生差别的事物
that produces the difference between a before and an after.
我们之前写的所有程序
All the other programs that we've written,
都不包含赋值
that have no assignments in them,
这些程序以怎样的顺序进行执行都没关系
the order in which they were evaluated didn't matter.
但是赋值比较特殊
But assignment is special,
它使时间中产生了一个时间点
it produces a moment in time.
因此在set!出现之前和之后中间有一个时间点，
So there is a moment before the set occurs and after,
使得在这个时间点之后
such that after this moment in time,
变量有了一个值，value
the variable has the value, value.
与这个变量之前的值无关
Independent of what value it had before,
set!改变了它的值
set! changes the value of the variable.
在此之前
Until this moment,
我们都没遇到过发生这样改变的情况
we had nothing that changed.
举例来说
So, for example,
我们可以想到的一件事是
one of the things we can think of
我们写的一些过程比如阶乘的程序
is that the procedures we write for something like factorial
事实上与数学中的阶乘函数完全相同
are in fact pretty much identical to the function factorial.
4的阶乘，如果我写fact4
Factorial of four, if I write fact4,
它将独立于它的上下文
independent of what context it's in,
也独立于我写几遍
and independent of how many times I write it,
我总能得到同样的结果
I always get the same answer.
结果永远是24
It's always 24.
它是参数到到结果的唯一映射
It's a unique map from the argument to the answer.
迄今为止，我们之前写的所有程序都是这样的
And all the programs we've written so far are like that.
然而，当我赋值的时候，一切就不同了
However, once I have assignment, that isn't true.
举个例子
So, for example,
如果我将count定义为1
if I were to define count to be one.
然后定义一个过程
And then I'm going to define also a procedure,
名为demo的简单过程
a simple procedure called demo,
它接受参数x，并执行下面的操作
which takes argument x and does the following operations.
首先set! x为x加1，
It first sets x to x plus one.
我勒个去，这看起来就像FORTRAN，是吧？
My gosh, this looksjust like FORTRAN, right--
只是用了些有趣的语法
in a funny syntax.
然后加上x count
And then add to x count,
哦，我刚犯了个错
Oh, I just made a mistake.
我的意思是
I want to say,
set! count为1加上count
set! count to one plus count.
就是我在这里定义的这个
It's this thing defined here.
然后x和count相加
And then plus x count.
然后就可以试着运行这个过程了
Then I can try this procedure.
让我们运行它
Let's run it.
假设我可以输入
So, suppose I get a prompt and I say,
我输入demo 3
demo 3
这里发生了什么？Well, what happens here?
发生的第一件事情是
The first thing that happens
count现在是1
is count is currently one.
现在，这是一个时间点
Currently, there is a time.
我们在讨论时间点
We're talking about time.
x的值为3
x gets three.
在这个时刻
At this moment,
count增加了，所以count是2
I say, oh yes, count is incremented, so count is two.
2加3等于5
two plus three is five.
所以结果是5
So the answer I get out is five.
然后我再一次，输入demo 3
Then I say, demo of say, three again.
结果是什么？
What do I get?
现在count是2，它不再是1了
Well, now count is two, it's not one anymore,
因为我让count加1了
because I have incremented it.
但现在我执行这个过程，
But now I go through this process,
x的值为3
three goes into x,
count变为1加count，因此现在是3了
count becomes one plus count, so that's three now.
这两个相加是6
The sum of those two is six,
所以结果是6
so the answer is six.
我们可以发现
And what we see
同样的表达式
is the same expression
却得到了不同的结果
leads to two different answers,
因为时间的作用
depending upon time.
所以demo不是函数
So demo is not a function,
它没有计算一个数学中的函数
does not compute a mathematical function.
事实上，你可以知道这是为什么
In fact, you could also see why now, of course,
因为这里是第一处代换模型失效的地方
this is the first place where the substitution model isn't going to work.
它弄死了代换模型
This kills the substitution model dead.
哲学家可能注意到一些小麻烦
You know, with quotation there were some little problems that a philosopher might notice
因为你不得不去担心在#TBD的时候能如何代换
with the substitutions, because you have to worry about what deductions you can make when you substitute into quotes,
如果你被允许代换的话
if you're allowed to do that at all.
但是
But
在这里代换模型已经死了
here the substitution model is dead,
他什么也不能做了
can't do anything at all.
因为
Because,
假设我想用代换模型来考虑count的代换
Supposing I wanted to use a substitution model to consider substituting for count?
如果我在这里和这里进行代换
Well, my gosh, if I substitute for here and here,
它们是不同的
they're different ones.
它不再是同一个count了
It's not the same count any more.
我得到了错误的结果
I get the wrong answer.
代换模型是一个静态的现象#TBD
The substitution model is a static phenomenon
它描述了真实的事物#TBD
describes things that are true
并且事物不会改变#TBD
and not things that change.
这里，我们的的真实变了#TBD
Here, we have truths that change.
那么，在我给出任何解释之前
OK, Well, before I give you any understanding of this,
这很糟糕
this is very bad.
我们失去了我们的计算模型
Now, we've lost our model of computation.
并且
And,
很快，我将不得不构建一个新的计算模型
pretty soon, I'm going to have to build you a new model of computation.
#TBD
But ours plays with this, just now, in an informal sense.
当然，你们已经看到的是
Of course, what you already see
当我做一些像赋值之类的事情时
is that when I have something like assignment,
我们所需要的模型
the model that we're going to need
与我们之前模型不同
is different from the model that we had before
在这个的模型中，像count或x这些符号
in that, the variables, those symbols like count, or x
不再关联于他们的值
are no longer going to refer to the values they have,
而是关联于某个储存这些值的地方
but rather to some sort of place where the value restored.
我们将不得不以这种方式思考一段时间
We're going to have to think that way for a while.
这将是一个很糟糕坏的事情
And it's going to be a very bad thing
并且会造成很多麻烦
and cause a lot of trouble.
所以，就像我说的，当我们创造糟糕的事物
And so, as I said, the very fact that we're inventing this bad thing,
意味着有更好的创造它的理由
means that there had better be a good reason for it,
否则，就是浪费时间和精力
otherwise, just a waste of time and a lot of effort.
让我们看看一些东西#TBD
Let's just look at some of it just to play.
假设我们写了函数式版本的阶乘
Supposing we write down the functional version,
传统意义中的那个函数式
functional meaning in the old style,
这个阶乘使用了迭代的过程
of factorial by an iterative process.
n的阶乘
我们要从m迭代到i
we're going to iterate of m and i,
就是说如果i大于n
which says if i is greater than n,
则结果是m
then the result is m,
否则
otherwise,
结果是迭代i和m的乘积
the result of iterating the product of i and m.
所以m将是我累积的结果
So m is going to be the product that I'm accumulating.
m就是这个乘积
m is the product.
然后我要把count加1
And the count I'm going to increase by one.
[闭合括号中]
Plus, ITER, ELSE, COND, define.
我要从这开始写
I'm going to start this up.
如今，你们应该能够没有任何障碍地阅读这类东西了
And these days, you should have no trouble reading something like this.
这里是一个累积的乘积，和一个计数器
What I have here is a product there being accumulated and a counter.
我让它们都从1开始
I start them up both at one.
我将不断让计数器增加
I'm going to buzz the counter up,
每个回合i变成i加1
i goes to i plus one every time around.
那是我们在过程中唯一设置的时间点
But that's only our putting a time on the process,
#TBD
each of this is just a set of truths,
true rules.
m将获得一个新的值，就是i乘m
And m is going to get a new values of i and m,
每一轮i乘以m
i times m each time around,
最终i将大于n，在那种情况下，结果就是m
and eventually i is going to be bigger than n, in which case, the answer's going to be m.
现在我给你们讲，#TBD
Now, I'm speaking to you, use time in this.
那是因为我知道计算机是怎么工作的
That's just because I know how the computer
works.
但是我没必要这么做
But I didn't have to.
这可以作为一个纯数学的解释
This could be a purely mathematical description at this point,
因为代换在这里可以工作
because substitution will work for this.
但是我们写一个类似的程序
But let's set right down a similar sort of program,
使用相同的算法
using the same algorithm,
但使用了赋值
but with assignments.
所以这个叫做函数式版本
So this is called the functional version.
我想写个命令式的版本的
I want to write down an imperative version.
n的阶乘
Factorial of n.
我要创建两个变量
I'm going to create my two variables.
把i的值初始化为1
Let i initialize itself to one,
m也初始化为1
and m be initialized to one, similar.
我们创建一个循环
We'll create a loop
如果i比n大，循环结束
which has COND greater than i, and if i is greater than n, we're done.
结果是m
And the result is m,
也就是我累积的乘积
the product I'm accumulating.
否则
Otherwise,
我要写下三件要做的事
I'm going to write down three things to do.
我要set! m为i与m的乘积
I'm going to set! m to the product of i and m,
set! i为i加1的和
set! i to the sum of i and one,
然后继续循环
and go around the loop again.
你们中的FORTRAN程序员应该觉得眼熟
Looks very familiar to you FORTRAN programmers.
[闭合括号中]
ELSE, COND, define,
语法挺有趣吧？
funny syntax though.
启动循环
Start the loop up,
程序写完了
and that's the program.
那么，这个程序
Now, this program,
我们应该怎么看它呢？
how do we think about it?
来看看我们在这看到了什么
Well, let's just say what we're seeing here.
这里有两个局部变量，i和m
There are two local variables, i and m,
它们都被初始化为1
that have been initialized to one.
在每一次循环里，我检测i是否大于n
Every time around the loop, I test to see if i is greater than n,
就是我们传入的参数
which is the input argument,
如果成立的话，结果就是累积在m中的乘积
and if so, the re sult is the product being accumulated in m.
然而，如果循环没有结束
However, if it's not the end of the loop,
如果我们的工作没有结束
if I'm not done,
则我们要把乘积变为i与当前乘积的结果
then what I'm going to do is change the product to be the result of multiplying i times the current product.
就是我们在这里做过的事情
Which is sort of what we were doing here.
除了这里我没有改动
Except here I wasn't changing.
我复制出了另外一份
I was making another copy,
因为代换模型就是你复制过程的体
because the substitution model says, you copy the body of the procedure
并将形式参数用实际参数代换
with the arguments substituted for the formal parameters.
这里我不担心复制
Here I'm not worried about copying,
在这里，我已经改变了m的值
here I've changed the value of m.
我也把i的值变成了i加1
I also then change the value of i to i plus one,
然后继续循环
and go buzzing around.
看起来是一样的程序
Seems like essentially the same program,
但是可能有一些犯错的机会
but there are some ways of making errors here
直到今天还存在
that didn't exist until today.
例如
For example,
如果我在赋值的时候
if I were to do the horrible thing
没有小心地写程序
of not being careful in writing my program
把两个赋值的顺序调换了
and interchange those two assignments,
程序计算的就不是相同的函数了
the program wouldn't compute the same function.
我得到了一个时间错误，因为这儿有个依赖关系
I get a timing error because there's a dependency
m依赖于i上一次的值
there's a dependency that m depends upon having the last value of i.
如果我先改变i的值
If I try change i first,
就会在乘以m的时候，得到错误的i值
then I've got the wrong value of i when I multiply by m.
在此之前不会存在这样的bug
It's a bug that wasn't available until this moment,
直到我们把某些包含时间的东西引入进来才发生
until we introduced something that had time in it.
如我所说的
So, as I said,
首先，我们需要一个新的计算模型
first we need a new model of computation,
然后，我们就不得不去找，搞这些坑爹事的好理由
and second, we have to be damn good reason for doing this kind of ugly thing.
有什么问题吗？
Are there any questions?
大声点说，David
Speak loudly, David
学生：我们现在引入了set
AUDIENCE: I'm confused about, we've introduced set now,
但是我们之前已经有let和define了
but we had let before and define before.
我不太清楚它们的区别
I'm confused about the difference between the three.
define不能像set一样用吗？
Wouldn't define work in the same situation as set
请详细讲讲
if you introduced it a bit?
教授：不，define是在第一次时创建某个东西时给它设置一个值用的
PROFESSOR: No, define is intended for setting something once the first time,
为了创建它
for making it, OK?
你永远也不会见到我在黑板上
You've never seen me write on a blackboard
在同一行写两个define
two defines in a row
为了让某个变量的旧值变成一个新的值
whose intention was to change the old value of some variable to a new one.
学生：这是一个约定俗成的规矩，还是--
AUDIENCE: Is that by convention or--
教授：不，这是有意为之的
PROFESSOR: No, it's intention.
The answer is,
举个例子
that, for example,
在一个过程内部
internal to a procedure,
两个define写在一行里是非法的
two defines in a row are illegal,
对于同一个变量define两次是非法的
two defines in a row of the same variable.
x 不能被define两次
x can't be defined twice.
而系统会不会捕获这个错误，就是另一个问题了
Whether or not a system catches that error is a different question,
但是我定下规矩
but I legislate to you
任何东西都只能define一次
that define happens once on anything.
现在，确实，在交互式调试中
Now, indeed, in interactive debugging,
我们打算让你与你的计算机交互时可以重新define一些东西
we intend that you interacting with your computer will redefine things,
所以这是交互式调试带来的一个特殊的异常
and so there's a special exception made for interactive debugging.
#TBD
But define is intended to mean to set up something
which will be forever that value after that point.
#TBD
It's as if all the defines were done at the beginning.
In fact, the only legal place to put a define
#TBD
in Scheme, internal to a procedure,
就是lambda表达式的开始
is just at the beginning of a lambda expression,
过程体的开始
the beginning of the body of a procedure.
现在，let当然与那个不一样
Now, let of course does nothing like either of that.
如果你想知道let发生了什么
I mean, if you look at what's happening with a let,
这个只会重新发生一次#TBD
this happens again exactly once.
它建立了一个i和m的值分别为1的上下文
It sets up a context where i and m are values one and one.
这个上下文存在于整个作用域中
That context exists throughout this scope,
即程序的范围之内
this region of the program.
然而，你不会认为let再次设置了i的值
However, you don't think of that let as setting i again.
它没有改变i的值
It doesn't change it.
因为let，i将永远不会变化
i never changes because of the let.
因为let，i才被创建
i gets created because of let.
实际上
In fact,
let是一个非常简单的想法
the let is a very simple idea.
let不会做别的事情
Let does nothing more,
它让var1的值为1
Let a variable one to have value one
我要把这些更规整地写下来
I'll write this down a little bit more neatly;
var1的值，是表达式e1的值
Let's write, var one have value, the value of expression e1,
var2的值，是表达式e2的值
and variable two, have this value of the expression e2,
在表达式e3中
in an expression e3,
#TBD与var1和var2的过程一样，它们是形式参数
is the same thing as a procedure of var one and var two, the formal parameters,
e3成为过程的体
and e3 being the body,
在这里，var1与e1的值绑定
where var one is bound to the value of e1,
var2与e2的值绑定
and var two gets the value of e2.
所以实际上，这是一个从代换的角度来看很容易理解的东西
So this is, in fact, a perfectly understandable thing from a substitution point of view.
其实就是同一个表达式的两种不同的写法
This is really the same expression written in two different ways.
事实上，系统真正的工作方式就是在运行之前，把代码翻译成这种形式
In fact, the way the actual system
works is this gets translated into this before anything happens.
学生：我还是不清楚是什么造成了let和define之间的区别
AUDIENCE: OK, I'm still unclear as then what makes the difference between a let and a define. They could--
教授:define就是个语法糖
PROFESSOR: A define is a syntactic sugar,
#TBD
whereby, essentially a bunch of variables get created by lets and then set up once.
那么，我们休息一会
OK, time for the first break, I think. Thank you.
[音乐]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
看
Well let's see.
我现在不得不重建计算模型
I now have to rebuild the model of computation,
所以你明白了那些机制是如何运作的
so you understand how some such mechanical mechanism could work
来完成我们刚才说的那些工作
that can do what we've just talked about.
我刚刚摧毁了你们的代换模型
I just recently destroyed your substitution model.
不幸的是，这个模型比代换模型要复杂得多
Unfortunately, this model is significantly more complicated than the substitution model.
这个模型叫环境模型
It's called the environment model.
我即将介绍一些术语
And I'm going to have to introduce some terminology,
无论如何，你知道这些术语都是很好的
which is very good terminology for you to know anyway. It's about names.
它是关于名字的
It's about names.
我们将要给事物拥有的名字和这些名字的用途命名
And we're going
to give names to the kinds of names things have and the way those names are used.
所以这是一个元解释，如果你想这么理解的话
So this is a meta-description, if you will.
不管怎样，这儿有一堆坑爹的术语
Anyway, there is a pile of an unfortunate terminology here,
是我们将需要这些来理解所谓的环境模型
but we're going to need this to understand what's called the environment model.
我们可能要做一点无聊的#TBD了
We're about to do a little bit of boring, dog-work here.
我们来看第一张张幻灯片
Let's look at the first transparency.
我们看到了一个术语“约束”的解释
And we see a description of a word called bound.
我们会说一个变量v
And we're going to say that a variable, v,
被约束在表达式e中
is bound in an expression, e,
如果e的含义没有被变量w的形式代换改变的话
if the meaning of e is unchanged by the uniform replacement of a variable w,
#TBD
for every occurrence of v in e.
这是一个很长的句子
Now that's a long sentence,
我想，在我们都被搞糊涂之前，我应该说得详细点。
so, I think, I'm going to have to say a little bit about that before we even fool around at all here.
我们这里讨论的是约束变量
Bound variables we're talking about here.
你们已经看到它们很多次了
And you've seen lots of them.
但你们可能不知道自己已经见过它们很多次了
You may not know that you've seen lots of them.
我猜在你们的逻辑中，你们看到一个逻辑变量
Well, I suppose in your logic you saw a logical variables like,
对于任意任何x，存在一个y，使得p为真，就像你在微积分课上学到的。
for every x there exists a y such that p is true of x and y from your calculus class.
这个变量x，这个变量y，它们被约束
This variable, x, and this variable, y, are bound,
因为
because,
这个表达式的含义
the meaning of this expression
不取决于
我用来描述x和y的具体字母
does not depend upon the particular letters I used to describe x and y.
如果我用w替换x
If I were to change the w for x,
则可以说对于任意w，存在一个y使得p为真
then said for every w there exists a y such that p is true of w and y,
它们其实是同一句话
it would be the same sentence.
这就是那句话的意思
That's what it means.
或者在另一个情况下，你们看到这是一个积分的描述
Or another case of this that you've seen is integral say,
对1+x的平方分之dx从0到1积分
from 0 to one of dx over one plus x square.
这就是你们经常见到的那种东西
Well that's something you see all the time.
这个x是一个约束变量
And this x is a bound variable.
如果我把它换成t
If I change that to a t,
这个表达式其实没有变化
the expression is still the same thing.
就是#TBD
This is a 1/4 of the arctan of one or something here.
是的，就是1的反正切
Yes, that's the arctan of one.
所以约束变量事实上很常见
So bound variables are actually fairly common,
如果你们接触过一些数学的话for those of you who have played a bit with mathematics.
好，让我们来到编程的世界
Well, let's go into the programming world.
#TBD
Instead of the quantifier being something like,
for every, or there exists, or integral,
#TBD
a quantifier is a symbol that binds a variable.
我们要使用#TBDlambda
And we are going to use the quantifier lambda
作为约束变量的一个必要的东西
as being the essential thing that binds variables.
#TBD
And so we have some nice examples here
like that procedure of one argument y which does the following thing.
它以一个参数x调用了过程
It calls the procedure of one argument x,
将x乘以y
which multiplies x by y,
#TBD
and applies that to three.
这个过程中包含两个约束变量
That procedure has the property there of two bound variables in it,
x和y
x and y
这个量词，lambda，约束了这个y
This quantifier, lambda here, binds this y,
这个量词lambda，约束了这个x
and this quantifier, lambda, binds that x.
因为，如果我用了一个没有出现在表达式中的任意符号，如w，
Because, if I were to take an arbitrary symbol does not occur in this expression like w
用w替换表达式中的所有y
and replace all y's with w's in this expression,
这个表达式仍与原来的相同
the expression is still the same,
是相同的过程
the same procedure.
这是一个重要的想法
And this is an important idea.
我们有这种东西的原因
The reason why we had such things like that
是一种流行趋势
is a kind of modularity.
如果有两个人写程序
If two people are writing programs,
并且他们在合作编程
and they work together,
在他们自己构建的小项目里用什么命名都没有关系
it shouldn't matter what names they use internal to their own little machines that they're building.
所以，实际上我想告诉你们
And so, what I'm really telling you there,
例如
is that, for example,
这个表达式等于，以y为参数的过程
this is equivalent to that procedure of one argument y which
#TBD
uses that procedure of one argument z which multiplies z by y.
因为没人关心我在这用什么
Because nobody cares what I used in here.
这是一个极好的例子
It's a nice example.
另一方面
On the other hand,
我有一些未被约束的变量
I have some variables that are not bound.
举个例子
And example,
这个对于一个参数x的过程
that procedure of one argument x
将x乘以y
which multiplies x by y
在这个例子中
In this case,
y没有被约束
y is not bound.
假设y的值是3
Supposing y had the value three,
z的值是4
and z had the value four,
那么这个过程就是把它的参数乘以3
then this procedure would be the thing that multiplies its argument by three.
如果我如果我把所有的y都用z来代替
If I were to replace every instance of y with z,
我将得到一个完全不同的过程，它会把参数乘以4
I would have a different procedure which multiplies every argument that's given by four.
事实上，我们给这种变量取了个名字
And, in fact, we have a name for such a variable.
我们把表达式e中的变量v叫做自由变量
Here, we say that a variable, v, is free in the expression, e,
if the meaning of the expression, e, is changed by the uniform replacement of a variable, w, not occurring in e
for every occurrence of v and e.
所以
So,
所以这就是为什么这个变量y，是一个自由变量
So that's why this variable over here, y, is a free variable.
所以，这个表达式里的自由变量
And so free variables in this expression--
另一个例子是
And other examples of that is that
对于一个参数y的过程
is that procedure of one argument y,
就像我们之前的那个一样
which is just what we had before,
使用对于参数x的过程
which uses that procedure of one argument x
将x与y相乘--
that multiplies x by y--
#TBD
use that on three.
这个过程中有一个自由变量
This procedure has a free variable in it
也就是这个星号
which is asterisk.
你看，因为
See, because,
如果它表示正常意义的乘法
if that has a normal meaning of multiplication,
如果我形式上将所有星号都以加号代替
then if I were to replace uniformly all asterisks with pluses,
这个表达式的含义就变了
then the meaning of this expression would change.
这就是自由变量的意思
That's what you mean by a free variable.
目前，你们已经学过了一些术语
So, so far you've learned some logician words
用它们可以解释名字的用法
which describe the way names are used.
我们要需要更进一步深入
Now, we have to do a little bit more playing around here,
再多了解一些
a little bit more.
我想给你们讲讲
I want to tell you about
变量是在哪里被定义的
about the regions are over which variables are defined.
你瞧
You see,
#TBD
we've been very informal about this up till now,
当然，你们中的一些，或者大部分人可能已经理解得很透彻了
and, of course, many of you have probably understood very clearly or most of you,
在这里被声明的x
that the x that's being declared here
只被定义在这里
is defined only in here.
这个x，只被定义在这里
This x is the defined only in here,
这个y，只被定义在这里
and this y is defined only in here.
我们给它取了个名字，叫作用域
We have a name for such an idea. It's called a scope.
我给你们再讲个术语
And let me give you another piece of terminology.
这个就比较复杂
It's a long story.
如果x是e中的一个约束变量
If x is a bound variable in e,
那么它是约束于一个lambda表达式中
then there is a lambda expression where it is bound.
获取约束变量的唯一方法就是通过lambda表达式
So the only way you can get a bound variable ultimately is by lambda expression.
你可能会担心
Then you may worry,
define是它的一个例外吗？
does define quite an exception to this?
#TBD
And it turns out, we could always arrange things so you don't need any defines.
一会我们就能看到了
And we'll see that in a while.
它一个非常神奇的东西
It's a very magical thing.
所以这里不需要define
So define really can go away.
实际上，唯一能创建名字的东西是lambda
The really, only thing that makes names is lambda .
那就是它的工作
That's its job.
多么的令人惊奇
And what's so amazing about a lot of things
很多东西你只凭借lambda就可以计算
is you can compute with only lambda.
但是，在任何情况下
But, in any case,
一个lambda表达式有一个地方来声明变量
a lambda expression has a place where it declares a variable.
我们把它称为形式参数列表
We call it the formal parameter list
或约束变量列表
and we say or the bound variable list.
我们说lambda表达式约束--这是一个动词
We say that the lambda expression binds -- so it's a verb
--约束了在约束变量列表里声明的变量
--binds the variables declared in it's bound variable list.
另外，表达式中定义变量的那些部分
In addition, those parts of the expression where the variable is defined,
是被一些声明所声明的
which was declared by some declaration
这些部分被叫做变量的作用域
is called the scope of that variable.
所以，这些是作用域
So these are scopes.
这是y的作用域
This is the scope of y.
这是x的作用域--
And this is the scope of x--
以此类推
that sort of thing.
好
OK,
现在我们有了足够多的术语
well, now we have enough terminology
用来理解如何建立一个新的计算模型了
to begin to understand how to make a new model for computation
因为，很重要的一点是
because the key thing going on here
我们摧毁了代换模型
is that we destroyed the substitution model,
我们现在不得不需要一个模型，来体现表示名字被关联到某些地方
and we now have to have a model that represents the names as referring to places.
因为，如果我们要改变某个东西
Because if we are going to change something,
我们就需要一个存它的地方
then we have a place where it's stored.
你看
You see,
如果一个名字只是关联于一个值
if a name only refers to a value,
如果我试图改变这个名字的含义
and if I tried to change the name's meaning,
这不怎么明确 well, that's not clear.
因为没有名字可以关联的地方
There's nothing that is the place that that name referred to.
我如何真正的去描述它呢？
How am I really saying it? There is nothing shared
没有东西在名字的所有实例之间共享
among all of the instances of that name.
我们真正的意思是，对于一个名字
And what we really mean, by a name,
#TBD
is that we fan something out.
我们为某个东西命名，然后你拿到了它
We've given something a name, and you have it,
你能得到它，是因为我给了你一个它的引用
and you have it, because I'm given you a reference to it,
我把对它的引用给了你
and I've given you a reference to it.
我们会看到很多相关的例子#TBD
And we'll see a lot about that.
所以我来教给你关于环境的知识
So let me tell you about environments.
我需要用一下头顶上的幻灯机I need the overhead projection machine,
谢谢你
thank you.
这里
And so here
是一堆环境结构
is a bunch of environment structures.
环境就是执行虚拟的代换的一种方法
An environment is a way of doing
substitutions virtually.
它代表了一个地方
It represents a place
是存储你的未完成的代换的地方
where something is stored which is the substitutions that you haven't done.
它是一个收集各种东西的地方
It's a place where everything accumulates,
在那里，变量的名字与值关联在一起
where the names of the variables are associated with the values they have
所以
such that,
当你问某个名字是什么意思的时候
when you say, what dose this name mean,
你要在一个环境中寻找答案
you look it up in an environment.
所以环境是一个函数
So an environment is a function,
或一张表
or a table,
或类似的东西
or something like that.
但它是一种结构化的表
But it's a structured sort of table.
它是由框架构成
It's made out of things called frames.
框架是环境的一部分Frames are pieces of environment,
它们被链接在一起
and they are chained together,
以某种很好的方式
in some nice ways,
就是叫做#TBD之类的东西
by what's called parent links or something like that.
这里
So here,
有一个环境结构
we have an environment structure
它由三个环境组成，分别是A，B和C
consisting of three environments, basically, A, B, and C.
D也是环境，但它和C是一样的
d is also an environment, but it's the same one,
它们共享了同一个环境
they share.
那就是赋值的精髓所在
And that's the essence of assignment.
如果我改变了一个变量
If I change a variable,
比如改变这个变量的值
a value of a valuable that lives here, like that one,
那么它将在所有地方都可见
it should be visible from all places that you're looking at it from.
用x来举例
Take this one, x.
如果我将x改为4
If I change the x to four,
在其他地方也是可见的
it's visible from other places.
但是我们现在不去关心这个
But I'm not going to worry about that right now.
过一会儿会详细讨论这个问题
We're going to talk a lot about that in a little while.
这里有什么？
What do we have here?
这些叫做框架。这是一个框架
Well, these are called frames. Here is a frame,
这是一个框架
here's a frame
这也是一个框架
and here's a frame.
A是一个环境
A is an environment which consists of
它由框架II
the table label which is frame two,
和框架I组成
followed by the table labeled frame one.
在这个环境中
And, in this environment,
在这个所谓的环境中，也就是框架II中
in say this environment, frame two,
x和y是被约束的
x and y are bound.
它们有值
They have values.
对不起，是在框架I中
Sorry, in frame one
在框架II中
In frame two,
z被约束
z is bound,
x被约束
and x is bound,
并且y也是被约束的
and y is bound,
但是我们看到的x的值
but the value of x that we see,
从这个角度来看
looking from this point of view,
是这个x，它的值是7
is this x. It's x is seven,
而不是这个值为3的x
rather than this one which is three.
我们称之为，这个x隐蔽了这个x
We say that this x shadows this x.
从环境III
From environment three--
从框架III
from frame three,
从环境B
from environment b,
它引用了框架III
which refers to frame three,
变量n 和y被约束，x也被约束
we have variables n and y bound and also x.
这个y把它隐蔽了
This y shadow this one.
从这个角度来看
So the value, looking from this point of view,
y的值是2
of y is two.
从这个角度来看
The value for looking from this point of view
m的值是1，x的值是3
and m is one. And the value, looking from this point of view, of x is three.
所以，我们有了一个
So there we have
由框架构成的非常简单的环境结构
a very simple environment structure made out of frames.
它们与过程的应用相一致
These correspond to the applications of procedures.
我们马上就会看到
And we'll see that in a second.
现在要给你们看看我们构建的一些其他的很好的小结构
So now I have to make you some other nice little structure that we build.
下一张幻灯片
Next slide,
我们可以看到一个对象
we see an object,
我们将要描绘它的过程
which I'm going to draw procedures.
这是一个过程
This is a procedure.
这个过程由两个部分组成
A procedure is made out of two parts.
这有点像cons
It's sort of like a cons.
不管怎样，它有两个部分
However, it's the two parts.
第一个部分指向一些代码
The first part refers to some code,
这些代码将会被执行
something that can be executed,
你可以把它视作一组指令
a set of instructions, if you will. You can think of it that way.
第二部分是环境
And the second part is the environment.
这个过程就是全部了
The procedure is the whole thing.
我们要用它
And we're going to have to use this
来捕获出现在过程中的自由变量的值
to capture the values of the free variables that occur in the procedure.
如果过程中出现一个变量，它不是约束变量就是自由变量
If a variable occurs in the procedure it's either bound in that procedure or free.
如果它是约束变量
If it's bound,
则它的值将很容易被找到
then the value will somehow be easy to find.
它将存在于某个很容易找到的环境中
It will be in some easy environment to get at.
如果它是自由变量
If it's free,
we're going to have to have something that goes with the procedure
that says where we'll go look for its value.
现在为什么的理由还不清楚
And the reasons why are not obvious yet,
但很快就要真相大白了
but will be soon.
这里有一个对象，它是个混合的对象
So here's a procedure object. It's a composite object
由一些代码和一个环境结构组成
consisting of a piece of code and a environment structure.
现在我要告诉你们一些全新的规则
Now I will tell you the new rules, the complete new rules,
关于执行的规则
for evaluation.
这里只有两条规则
The first rule is-- there's only two of them.
这些规则与代换模型规则相对应
These correspond to the substitution model rules.
第一条规则是用来解决
And the first one has to do with
如何把一个过程，应用到它参数上的问题的
how do you apply a procedure to its arguments?
程序对象被应用于一组参数
And a procedural object is applied to a set of arguments
是通过构建一个新的框架来完成
by constructing a new frame.
那个框架将包含形式参数
That frame will contain the mapping of the former parameters to the actual
parameters
对调用中使用的实际参数的映射
of the arguments that were supplied in the call.
如你所知
As you know,
当我们建立一个过程，如lambda x， x乘y
when we make up a call to a procedure like lambda x times x y,
然后我们以3为参数调用它
and we call that with the argument three,
那么我们需要某个从x到3的映射
then we're going to need some mapping of x to three.
这与之前的代换是一样的
It's the same thing as later substituting,
在旧的模型中，x代换为3
if you will, the three for the x in the old model.
所以我要建立一个框架
So I'm going to build a frame which contains x equals three
在框架中包含x等于3的这个信息
as the information in that frame.
现在
Now,
过程的体即将被执行
the body of the procedure will then have to be evaluated which is this,
它将在一个环境中执行
and will be evaluated in an environment
这个环境是由我们创建的新框架组合而成
which is constructed by adjoining the new frame that we just made
它是我们所应用的哦成的一部分
to the environment which was part of the procedure that we applied.
所以，举个例子
So I'm going to make a little example of that here.
假设我有一些环境
Supposing I have some environment.
画个方框代表它
Here's a frame which represents it.
以及一些过程--我画圆来代表它们，因为这比小三角形好画--
And some procedure-- which I'm going to draw with circles here because it's easier than little triangles--
抱歉，是菱形
Sorry, those are rhombuses,
小块菱形的果冻之类的东西
rhomboidal little pieces of fruit jelly or something.
这有一个使用这个环境的过程
So here's a procedure which takes this environment.
这个过程有一些代码
And the procedure has a piece of code,
是一个lambda表达式
which is a lambda expression,
约束了x和y
which binds x and y
然后执行了表达式e
and then executes an expression, e.
这是一个过程
And this is the procedure.
我们叫它p
We'll call it p.
我希望将这个过程应用于3和4
I wish to apply that procedure to three and four.
所以我在这写(p 3 4)
So I want to do p of three and four.
我要做的事情是，是创建一个新的框架
What I'm going to do, of course, is make a new frame.
我建立了一个框架
I build a frame
框架中x等于3
which contains x equals three,
y等于4
and y equals four.
我要把这个框架
I'm going to connect that frame
连接到这一个框架上
to this frame over here.
对于这个环境
And then this environment,
我把它叫做B
with I will call b,
我会在这个环境中执行e的体
is the environment in which I will evaluate the body of e.
现在
Now,
e可能包含了x和y的引用以及一些别的东西
e may contain references to x and y and other things.
x和y的值在这里
x and y will have values right here.
其他的变量的值在这里
Other things will have their values here.
怎样才能获取这个框架呢？
How do we get this frame?
我们通过过程构建来完成
That we do by the construction of procedures
这就是另一条规则了
which is the other rule.
请看下一张幻灯片
And I think that's the next slide.
规则二
Rule two,
当一个lambda表达式被执行时
when a lambda expression is evaluated,
相对于某个特定的环境--
relative to a particular environment--
看
See,
获取一个过程的方式就是执行一个lambda表达式
the way I get a procedure is by evaluating the lambda expression.
这里有一个lambda表达式
Here's a lambda expression.
通过执行它
By evaluating it,
我获得了一个可以应用于3的过程
I get a procedure which I can apply to three.
现在lambda表达式
Now this lambda expression
在一个y已被定义的环境中执行
is evaluated in an environment where y is defined.
我希望这个过程的体中包括的y是自由变量
And I want the body of this which contains a free version of y.
在这里面，y是自由变量
y is free in here,
它在其他的地方都是被约束的
it's bound over the whole thing,
但在这里是自由变量
but it's free over here.
我想让这个y成为它
I want that y to be this one.
我在y被创建的环境中执行这个过程的体
I evaluate this body of this procedure in the environment where y was created.
#TBD
That's this kind of thing, because that was done by application.
现在
Now,
如果我还想查找y的值
if I ever want to look up the value of y,
我就必须知道它在哪
I have to know where it is.
因此，这个过程在被创建时
Therefore, this procedural was created,
过程的创建，也就是lambda表达式的执行结果
the creation of the procedure which is the result of evaluating that lambda expression
最好是获取一个指针或记住y被约束在哪个框架中
had better capture a pointer or remember the frame in which y was bound.
这就是这个规则的内容
So that's what this rule is telling us.
那么，举个例子
So, for example,
如果我恰好执行了一个lambda表达式
if I happen to be evaluating a lambda expression,
在e中的lambda表达式
lambda expression in e,
#TBD
lambda of say, x and y, let's call it g in e,
执行它
evaluating that.
这些事的意义就是我现在构建了一个过程对象
all that means is I now construct a procedure object.
e是某个环境
e is some environment.
有个指针指向e
e is something which has a pointer to it.
我构建了一个过程对象指向了这个环境
I construct a procedure object that points up to that environment,
它的代码
where the code of that
是一个lambda表达式，或者其他可以翻译为lambda表达式的东西
is a lambda expression or whatever that translates into.
而这就是一个过程
And this is the procedure.
所以这个产物对我来说
So this produces for me--
这个对象
this object here,
这个环境指针
this environment pointer,
获取了lambda表达式执行所处于的环境
captures the place where this lambda expression was evaluated,
定义所使用的环境
where the definition was used,
创建一个过程时的定义所用的环境
where the definition was used to make a procedure,
从而创建了过程
to make the procedure.
所以，它将环境从定义过程的地方取出
So it picks up the environment from the place where that procedure was defined,
将它保存在过程自己内部
stores it in the procedure itself,
之后当过程被调用时
and then when the procedure is used,
它在被定义时的环境
the environment where it was defined is extended
将由新的框架扩充
with the new frame.
这给了我们一个放置有值的变量的地方
So this gives us a locus for putting where a variable has a value.
举个例子
And, for example,
如果有很多东西指向那这个环境
if there are lots of guys pointing in at that environment,
它们就会共享这个环境
then they share that place.
我们很快就会更进一步了解它们
And we'll see more of that shortly.
现在你们有了一个新模型
Well, now you have a new model
我们用它来理解程序的执行
for understanding the execution of programs.
我觉得现在我应该解答一些问题了
I suppose I'll take questions now,
之后我们再继续
and then we'll go on and use that for something.
学生：这么说是对的吗？
AUDIENCE: Is it right to say then,
环境就是被连接在一起的框架开始的地方--
the environment is that linked chain of frames starting with--
教授：对的
PROFESSOR: That's right.
学生：通过它能够取回所有的框架？
AUDIENCE:  working all the way back?
教授：是的，环境是一系列被连接在一起的框架
PROFESSOR: Yes, the environment is a sequence of frames linked together.
我对它的理解是，它是指向第一个框架的指针
And the way I like to think about it, it's the pointer to the first one,
因为一旦你获得了它，你就能拿到所有的框架
because once you've got that you've got them all.
还有谁有问题吗？
Anybody else?
学生：有这种可能吗？在两个不同的环境中执行
AUDIENCE: Is it possible to evaluate a procedure or to define a procedure in two different environments
或定义一个过程，使得它有不同的行为，并且有指向两个环境的指针--
such that it will behave differently, and have pointers to both--
教授：噢，是的。同一个过程不会有两个不同环境
PROFESSOR: Oh, yes. The same procedure is not going to have two different environments.
同样的代码
The same code,
同样的lambda表达式
the same lambda expression
可以在两个不同的环境中执行
can be evaluated in two environments producing two different procedures.
每个过程--
Each procedure--
学生：它们的定义有同样的名字，它们的操作--
AUDIENCE: Their definition has the same name. Their operation--
教授：它们定义是写起来是一样的，使用同样的字母
PROFESSOR: The definition is written the same, with the same characters.
我能执行那一组字母
I can evaluate that set of characters,
或定义的列表结构之类的东西
whatever, that list structure that defines,
那只是文本表示
that is the textual representation.
我可以在两个不同环境种执行它，产生两个不同的过程
I can evaluate that in two different environments producing two different procedures.
每一个过程
Each of those procedures
有它们自己的一组局部变量
has its own local sets of variables,
我们很快就会看到
and we'll see that right now.
还有其他人吗？
Anybody else?
好，谢谢你们，我们休息一会
OK, thank you. Let's take a break.
[音乐]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
我现在已经为你们做了一件非常糟糕的事情
Well, now I've done this terrible thing to you.
我引入了一个非常复杂的东西
I've introduced a very complicated thing,
赋值
assignment,
它摧毁了我们程序中大部分的，有趣的数学特性
which destroys most of the interesting mathematical properties of our programs.
我为什么要做这件事呢
Why should I have done this?
这样做可能有什么好处吗？
What possible good could this do?
很明显，这不是一个什么好东西
Clearly not a nice thing,
因此我最好有一个好的解释
so I better have a good excuse.
让我们来小小地玩一下
Well, let's do a little bit of playing,
首先，我们写些非常有趣的带赋值的程序
first of all, with some very interesting programs that have assignment.
来理解它们的特殊之处
Understand something special about them
这些特殊之处使赋值变得有价值
that makes them somewhat valuable.
我们从一个非常简单的程序开始
Start with a very simple program
我把这个程序叫做make-counter
I'm going to call make-counter.
我要把它定义为
I'm going to define make-counter
接受一个参数n的过程
to be a procedure of one argument n
并且它的返回值是一个没有参数的过程--
which returns as its value a procedure of no arguments--
一个生成过程的过程--
a procedure that produces a procedure--
这个过程把n的值设为n加1
which sets n to the increment of n
并且返回n的值
and returns that value of n.
现在，我们要研究它的行为
Now we're going to investigate the behavior of this.
它很有趣
It's a sort of interesting thing.
为了研究它的行为
In order to investigate the behavior,
我需要建立一个环境模型
I have to make an environment model,
因为我们不能通过其他的方式来理解它
because we can't understand this any other way.
所以我们开始吧
So let's just do that.
我们从这里开始
We start out with some sort of--
假设机器天生就有一个全局的环境
let's say there is a global environment that the machine is born with.
我们把它叫做全局环境
Global we'll call it.
它内部有一堆初始化的东西
And it's going to have in it a bunch of initial things.
我们都知道它里面有什么
We all know what it's got.
这里面有+和*
It's got things in it like say, plus, and times,
/，-和CAR
and quotient, and difference, and CAR,
以此类推
and etcetera,
有很多东西
lots of things.
我不知道它们是什么
I don't know what they are,
一些#TBD
some various squiggles
机器一开始就有这些特性
that are the things the machine is born with.
通过在这做定义
And by doing the definition here,
我要做的是--
what I plan to do--
我在干什么呢？
Well, what am I doing?
我要把它关联到全局环境上
I'm doing this relative to the global environment.
这是我的环境指针
So here's my environment pointer.
为了达到那个目的，我要执行这个lambda表达式In order to do that I have to evaluate this lambda expression.
这意味着我创建了一个过程对象That means I make a procedure object.
所以，我要在这创建一个过程对象
So I'm going to make a procedure object here.
这个过程对象
And the procedure object has,
由于在它被定义的地方
as the place it's defined,
有一个全局的环境
the global environment.
这个过程对象包括了
The procedure object contains
以n为参数的过程的代码some code that represents a procedure of one argument n
它返回一个不接受参数的过程来做一些事情
which returns a procedure of no arguments which does something.
定义是一种改变环境的方法
And the define is a way of changing this environment,
所以我把make-counter加入全局环境中
so that I now add to it a make-counter,
这是对于特殊的东西定义的一个特殊的规则
a special rule for the special thing defined.
但它其实是
But what that is,
它给了我们一个指针，指向那个过程
is it gives me that pointer to that procedure.
所以现在全局环境中也有了make-counter
So now the global environment contains make-counter as well.
现在，我们要进行一些操作
Now, we're going to do some operations.
我要用它来创建一些计数器
I'm going to use this to make some counters.
我们将看到什么是计数器
We'll see what a counter is.
所以我们定义
So let's define
c1为一个从0开始的计数器
c1 to be a counter beginning at 0.
根据模型，我们知道如何做这个了
Well, we know how to do this now, according to the model.
我需要执行在全局环境中的make-counter
I have to evaluate the expression make-counter in the global environment,
make-counter 0
make-counter of 0.
我查找make-counter，发现它是一个过程
Well, I look up make-counter and see that it's a procedure.
我将要应用这个过程
I'm going to have to apply that procedure.
我应用这个过程的方式
The way I apply the procedure
就是构建一个框架
is by constructing a frame.
所以我构建了一个框架
So I construct a frame
它内部有一个n的值
which has a value for n in it
这个值是0
which is 0
它的父环境and the parent environment
是make-counter的定义的环境
is the one which is the environment of definition of make-counter.
所以我已经通过将make-counter应用于0上，而创建了一个环境
So I've made an environment by applying make-counter to 0.
现在，我需要执行make-counter的体
Now, I have to evaluate the body of make-counter,
就是那个环境中的lambda表达式
which is this lambda expression, in that environment.
执行这个体
Well evaluating this body,
它是一个lambda表达式
this body is a lambda expression.
执行一个lambda表达式，意味着创建一个过程对象
Evaluate a lambda expression means make a procedure object.
所以我将创建一个过程对象
So I'm going to make a procedure object.
And that procedure object has
the environment it was defined in being that,
where n was defined to be 0.
And it has some code,
which is the procedure of no arguments which does
something,
that sets something,
and returns n.
And this thing
is going to be the object,
which in the global environment, will have the name c1.
所以我们在这建立一个名字，c1
So we construct a name here, c1,
并且说c1等于这个过程
and say that equals that.
现在，再来创建另一个计数器
Now, but also make another counter,
通过make-counter创建c2
c2 to be make-counter say,
让它从10开始
starting with 10.
然后我执行同样的步骤
Then I do essentially the same thing.
我应用这个make-counter过程
I apply the make-counter procedure, which I got from here,
建立另一个n等于10的框架
to make another frame with n being 10.
全局环境作为它的父环境
That frame has the global environment as its parent.
然后我构建一个过程
I then construct a procedure
以这个框架作为它定义的环境
which has that as it's frame of definition.
它的代码是
The code of it is
一个不需要参数，并做了某些工作的过程
the procedure of no arguments which does something.
And it does a set, and so on.
然后返回n
And n comes out.
这就是c2
And c2 is this.
好，你们应该发现，某些东西开始变得有趣了
Well, you're already beginning to see something fairly interesting.
这里有两个n
There are two n's here.
它们不是同一个n
They are not one n.
每当我调用make-counter的时候
Each time I called make-counter,
我就创建了另一个n的实例
I made another instance of n.
它们彼此独立，没有关联
These are distinct and separate from each other.
现在，我们来使用一下这些计数器
Now, let's do some execution, use those counters.
如果此时，我调用c1，会发生什么？
Well, what happens if I say, c1 at this point?
我会在这里查找
Well, I go over here,
发现c1是一个过程
and I say, oh yes, c1 is a procedure.
我要不带参数地调用这个过程
I'm going to call this procedure on no arguments,
因为它不需要参数
but it has no parameters.
对吧？
That's right.
它的体是什么呢？
What's its body?
我得在这里查找，因为我没有写下来
Well, I have to look over here, because I didn't write it down.
这个体是将n设置为n加1
It said, set n to one plus n
并且返回n
and return n,
就是把n增大1
increment n.
n看起来应该是这一个
Well, the n it sees is this one.
所以我把这个n增大1
So I increment that n.
它变成了1
That becomes one,
然后返回了1
and I return the value one.
之后我调用c2
Supposing I then called c2.
我会做什么？
Well, what do I do?
c2是相同的过程
I say c2 is this procedure which does the same thing,
但这个n
but here's the n.
它变成了11
It becomes 11.
所以返回值是11
And so I have an 11 which is the value.
然后我们再来调用一下c1
I then can say, let's try c1 again.
c1是这个
c1 is this,
它是2
that's two,
所以结果是2
so the answer is two.
然后调用c2
And c2
然后c2通过同样的方法，返回了12
gives me a 12 by the same method,
它在这里进行查找
by walking down here looking at that
发现了n，并把它加1
and saying, here's the n, I'm incrementing.
这里就是计算对象
So what I have are computational objects.
这里有两个计数器
There are two counters,
每一个都有各自独立的局部状态
each with its own independent local state.
我们再进一步
Let's talk about this a little.
这是个奇怪的东西
This is a strange thing.
什么是对象？
What's an object?
这个概念并不明确
It's not at all obvious what an object is.
我们倾向于以对象的角度思考
We like to think about objects,
因为这样思考比较经济
because it's economical to think that way.
这是一种智力上的经济
It's an intellectual economy.
我是一个对象
I am an object.
你们都是对象
You are an object.
我们不是一样的对象
We are not the same object.
我可以把世界分为两部分
I can divide the world into two parts,
我和你
me and you,
以及其他的东西
and there's other things as well,
那么
such that
大多数对于我的讨论
most of the things I might want to discuss about my workings
不会影响到你
do not involve you,
大多数对于你的讨论不会牵涉到我
and most of the things I want to discuss about your workings don't involve me.
我有血压
I have a blood pressure,
体温
a temperature,
呼吸频率
a respiration rate,
血液中有确定的血糖值
certain amount of sugar in my blood,
数不清的，数以千计的状态变量--上百万实际上
and numerous, thousands, of state variables-- millions actually,
我不知道具体有多少
or I don't know how many--
以物理学观点，我拥有大量的状态变量
huge numbers of state variables in the physical sense
如果将我视为一个粒子的话which represent the state of me as a particle,
而你也有许许多多这样的变量
and you have gazillions of them as well.
大多数我的变量与大多数你的变量是解耦的无关的
And most of mine are uncoupled to most of yours.
所以可以计算我的属性
So we can compute the properties of me
而不用太担心你的属性
without worrying too much about the properties of you.
如果我们需要把我们两个放在一起计算
If we had to work about both of us together,
那么我们需要考虑的状态的数量，就是你与我的状态的数量的乘积
than the number of states that we have to consider is the product of the number of states you have and the number of states I have.
但这个方法只是一种计数
But this way it's almost a sum.
#TBD
Now, indeed there are forces that couple us.
我对你讲话，你的状态就变了
I'm talking to you and your state changes.
我看着你，我的状态就变了
I'm looking at you and my state changes.
因此，我的变量中的一小部分
Some of my state variables, a very few of them,
与你的一些变量是耦合的
therefore, are coupled to yours.
如果你突然大喊大叫
If you were to suddenly yell very loud,
我的血压就会升高
my blood pressure would go up.
将世界看作是由独立的变量
However, and it may not be always appropriate
和独立的粒子组成的是不恰当的
to think about the world as being made out of independent states and independent particles.
在像量子力学这样的东西里存在大量的bug
Lots of the bugs that occur in things like quantum mechanics,
或者当我们思考像量子力学之类的东西的时候，会在我们的脑海中产生bug
or the bugs in our minds that occur when we think about things like quantum mechanics,
由于这样的事实，
are due the fact that we are trying to think about things
我们会竭尽全力地去将事物分解为相互独立的部分来看待
being broken up into independent pieces,
而事实上事物的耦合程度，远远大于在表面所看到的
when in fact there's more coupling than we see on the surface,
即便这样，我们仍像那样思考
or that we want to believe in,
是因为我们希望高效并且有效的进行计算
because we want to compute efficiently and effectively.
我们被培养成以那种方式进行思考
We've been trained to think that way.
大家看
Well, let's see.
我们如何才能知道我们是否有对象？
How would we know if we had objects at all?
#TBD
How can we tell if we have objects?
通过思考一些视觉误差
Consider some possible optical illusions.
就能解答这个问题
This could be done.
这几截粉笔不完全相同
These pieces of chalk are not appropriately identical,
但是我觉得你看不出来他们的区别
but supposing you couldn't tell the difference of them by looking at them.
有一种可能
Well, there's a possibility
是这一切都是我们与镜子的游戏
that this all a game I'm playing with mirrors.
它们真的是同一截粉笔
It's really the same piece of chalk,
但你看到了两个
but you're seeing two of them.
你怎么知道你看到的是一个还是两个呢？
How would you know if you're seeing one or two?
我只知道有一种方法可以确定
Well, there's only one way I know.
抓起其中一个并且改变它
You grab one of them and change it
然后看看另一个有没有跟着变化
and see if the other one changed.
而另一个没有变化
And it didn't, so there's two of them.
所以这里有两截粉笔
so there's two of them.
另一方面
And, on the other hand,
事物还有一些其他的类似的纠结属性
there is some other screwy properties of things like that.
例如，我们怎么才知道某个东西是否改变了呢？
Like, how do we know if something changed?
我们需要在它改变之前和之后进行观察We have to look at it before and after the change.
改变就是赋值
The change is an assignment,
它是时间中的一个时刻
it's a moment in time.
但是那意味着我们需要知道，我们看到的是否是同一个
But that means we have to know it was the same one that we're looking at.
所以一些东西非常奇怪
So some very strange, and unusual, and obscure,
不同寻常并且晦涩难懂
and obscure, and -- I don't understand
并且我不理解与赋值
the problems associated with assignment,
变化以及对象有关的问题
and change, and objects.
这些东西可能变得非常非常糟糕
These could get very, very bad.
例如
For example,
我，是一个特定的人
here I am, I am a particular person,
一个特定的对象
a particular object.
现在，我可以拿出小刀
Now, I can take out my knife,
修剪我的指甲
and cut my fingernail.
一片指甲掉在了桌子上
A piece of my fingernail has fallen off onto the table.
我相信自己和一秒钟之前的自己，是同一个人I believe I am the same person I was a second ago,
但在物理上并不是分毫不差
but I'm not physically the same in the slightest.
我已经改变了
I have changed.
为什么我还是同一个人呢？
Why am I the same?
什么能认定我的身份呢？
What is the identity of me?
我不知道
I don't know.
除非我有某种身份证明
Except for the fact that I have some sort of identity.
我觉得，由于引入赋值和对象
And so, I think by introducing assignment and objects,
我们不得不去面对这种
we have opened ourselves up to all the horrible questions of philosophy
困扰了哲学家们上千年的哲学问题
that have been plaguing philosophers for some thousands of years about this sort of thing.
这也是相比之下，数学清晰得多的原因
It's why mathematics is a lot cleaner.
我看看来看看动作和身份认证
Let's look at the best things I know to say about actions and identity.
动作a，对于对于某个对象x有影响
We say that an action,
a, had an effect on an object, x,
换句话说
or equivalently,
x被a改变
that x was changed by a,
如果某个属性p，在a作用于x之前为真
if some property, p, which was true of x before a,
在a作用于x之后为假
became false of x after a.
我们测试一下
Let's test.
这也意味着，我必须#TBD
It still means I have to have the x before and after.
或者，换句话说
Or, the other way of saying this is,
我们说两个对象x和y是同一个东西
we say that two objects x and y are the same for any action
是由于任何动作对x的影响将对y有同样的影响
which has an effect on x has the same effect on y
然而，就像我说的
However, objects are very useful,
对象在智力经济上是非常有用的
as I said, for intellectual economy.
对于它们来说非常有用的东西之一
One of the things that's incredibly useful about them,
就是对于这个世界
is that the world is,
我们习惯于把它认为是由带有独立状态的独立对象所构成的
made out of independent objects with independent local state.
我们喜欢以那样的的方式来思考，虽然那并不完全正确
We like to think that way, although it isn't completely true.
当我们要写一个非常复杂的程序
When we want to make very complicated programs
来应对这样一个世界时
that deal with such a world,
如果我们希望这些程序可以被我们理解
if we want those programs to be understandable by us
并且也是可修改的
and also to be changeable,
那么如果世界改变了，我们只需要稍微改动一下程序
so that if we change the world we change the program only a little bit,
#TBD
then we want there to be connections, isomorphism,
between the objects in the world and the objects in our mental model.
世界的模块化，使我们的程序得以模块化
The modularity of the world can give us the modularity in our programming.
所以我们发明了面向对象编程
So we invent things
called object-oriented programming and things like that
使我们获得那样的力量
to provide us with that power.
但是，它甚至更简单
But it's even easier.
让我们玩一个小游戏
Let's play a little game.
通过这个游戏给你展示一个例子
I want to play a little game, show you an even easier example of where
赋值表达式可以增强模块化的例子
modularity can be enhanced by using an assignment statement, judiciously.
有一件我想让你深刻记住的事
One thing I want to enforce and impress on you,
就是不要像在FORTRAN，Basic或者Pascal里一样使用赋值语句
is don't use assignment statements the way you use it in FORTRAN or Basic or something or Pascal,
你不那样做，也能达到目的
to do the things you don't have to do with it.
这不是思考大多数事情的正确方式
It's not the right way to think for most things.
有些时候它是必要的
Sometimes it's essential,
或者可能是必要的
or maybe it's essential.
我们一会更深入地去研究
We'll see more about that too.
我要给你展示一个有趣的游戏
OK, let me show you a fun game here.
从前有一个数学家
There was mathematician
叫做Cesaro
by the name of Cesaro--or Cesaro, Cesaro I suppose it is--
他发现了一个很绝妙的计算pi的方法
who figured out a clever way of computing pi.
如果我有两个随机数
It turns out that if I take to random numbers
两个随机的整数
two integers at random,
计算它们的最大公约数
and compute the greatest common divisor,
结果可能是1，或者不是1
their greatest common divisor is either one or it's not one.
如果是1，它们没有公约数
If it's one, then they have no common divisors.
如果它们的最大公约数是1
If their greatest common divisor is one--
这两个随机数
the probability that two random numbers,
最大公约数为1的，两个随机生成的数
two numbers chosen at random, has as greatest common divisor one
与pi有关系
is related to pi.
事实上
In fact--
是的，这很奇怪
yes, it's very strange--
当然有其他计算pi的方法，像#TBD之类的的方法
of course there are other ways of computing pi, like dropping pins on flags, and things like that, and sort of the same kind of thing.
两个随机生成的n1和n2的最大公约数
So the probability of that the GCD of number one and number two, two random numbers chosen,
是6/pi^2
is 6 over pi squared.
我不准备证明这个
I'm not going to try to prove that.
事实上这不难，并且有些有趣
It's actually not too hard and sort of fun.
我们为什么会做出这样的推断呢？
How would we estimate such probability?
我们进行可能性推断的方式
Well, the way we do that,
是做大量的实验
is by doing lots of experiments,
去计算成功的试验
and then computing the ratios of the ones that come out one way
与试验总次数的比率
to the total number of experiments we do.
这种方法叫做蒙特卡洛方法
It's called Monte Carlo,
在其他的例如有巨量的变量的地方--
and it's useful in other contexts for doing things like integrals where you have lots and lots of variables--
#TBD是非常有用的
the space which is limiting the dimensions you are doing you integral in.
回到这里
But going back to here,
我们来看看这张幻灯片
Let's look at this slide,
我们可以用Cesaro的方法来推测pi的值
We can use Cesaro's method for estimating pi
#TBD
with n trials by taking the square root of six over a Monte Carlo,
a Monte Carlo experiment with n trials,
使用了Cesaro试验
using Cesaro's experiment,
where Cesaro's experiment is the test of whether the GCD of two random numbers--
你可以看到，我已经在这里进行了一些赋值
And you can see that I've already got some assignments in here,
就像我写的这样
just by what I wrote.
这个在括号中的rand
The fact that this word rand, in parentheses,
这个过程调用
therefore, that procedure call,
生成了一个其他的值
yields a different value than this one,
至少是我写的这样所假设的at least that's what I'm assuming by writing this this way,
这表明这不是一个函数
indicates that this is not a function,
在变化时，里面会有一个内部状态
that there's internal state in it which is changing.
如果两个随机数的最大公约数等于1
If the GCD of those two random numbers is equal to one,
这就是一次实验#TBD
that's the experiment.
那么我有了一个用来推算pi的值的实验方法
So here I have an experimental method for estimating the value of pi.
我可以简单地将这个问题分为两个部分
Where, I can easily divide this problem into two parts.
一部分是Cesaro的特殊的蒙特卡洛实验，就像你刚才看到那个
One is the specific Monte Carlo experiment of Cesaro, which you just saw,
另一部分就是进行蒙特卡洛实验的常规技巧
and the other is the general technique of doing Monte Carlo experiments.
就是这个
And that's what this is.
如果我想进行n次蒙特卡洛实验
If I want to do Monte Carlo experiments with n trials,
一个确定次数的实验，和一个特定的实验#TBD
a certain number of trials, and a particular experiment,
我进行实验的方法就是
the way I do that
构建一个迭代过程
is I make a little iterative procedure
这个过程有两个变量，分别是试验的剩余次数，和通过次数
which has variable the number of trials remaining and the number trials that have been passed,
就是结果为真的次数
that I've gotten true.
如果剩余次数为0
And if the number remaining is 0,
结果就是通过的次数除以总次数
then the answer is the number past divided by this whole number of trials,
即对可能性的估计
was the estimate of the probability.
如果剩余次数不是0
And if it's not,
如果还有试验要做
if I have more trials to do,
那么接下来我们就进行一次试验
then let's do one. We do an experiment.
我们调用一次没有参数的实验的过程
We call the procedure which is experiment on no arguments.
我们进行这个试验
We do the experiment
如果实验结果为真
and then, if that turned out to be true,
我们继续循环
we go around the loop
将试验通过次数加1
decrementing the number of experiments we have to do by one
试验剩余次数减1and incrementing the number that were passed.
如果实验的结果为假
And if the experiment was false,
我们继续循环
we just go around the loop
剩余试验次数减1
decrementing the number of experiments remaining
试验通过次数保持不变
and keeping the number passed the same.
我们以trial为剩余次数，0为通过次数开始迭代
We start this up iterating over the total number of trials with 0 experiments past.
多么简洁的小程序啊
A very elegant little program.
我不一定非要进行Cesaro的实验
And I don't have to just do this with Cesaro's experiment,
它可以用来进行很多种蒙特卡洛实验
it could be lots of Monte Carlo experiments I might do.
当然，它依赖于某种随机数生成器的存在
Of course, this depends upon the existence of some sort of random number generator.
随机数生成器通常是像这种的东西
And random number generators generally look something like this.
这是一个随机数生成器--
There is a random number generator--
实际上它就是一个，进行类似于计数操作的过程is in fact a procedure which is going to do something just like the counter.
它会把x的值更新为
It's going to update an x
将某个函数应用于x的结果
to the result of applying some function to x,
这个函数是
where this function
你可能在Kunth写的关于编程细节的书中找到的某种复杂的函数
is some screwy kind of function that you might find out in Knuth's books on the details of programming.
他写了这些充满了编程细节的绝妙的书
He does these wonderful books that are full of the details of programming,
因为我记不住随机数生成器该怎样写
because I can't remember how to make a random number generator,
但我可以在书里找出一个来用
but I can look it up there, and I can find out.
最后，我返回了x的值
And then, eventually, I return the value of x
也就是随机数生成器的内部状态变量
which is the state variable internal to the random number generator.
这个状态变量以某种方式被初始化
That state variable is initialized somehow,
从而获得了一个值
and has a value.
这个过程被定义在那个变量被约束的上下文中
And this procedure is defined in the context where that variable
所以你在这看到的，是一个隐藏的本地状态
So this is a hidden piece of local state that you see here.
这个过程定义在那个上下文中
And this procedure is defined in that context.
现在，那就是一个非常容易的事情了
Now, that's a very simple thing to do.
并且它非常的好用
And it's very nice.
设想，我不想用赋值
Supposing, I didn't want to use assignments.
假设我想写一个不带赋值的程序
Supposing, I wanted to write this program without assignments.
我将遇到什么困难？
What problems would I have?
让我们来看看
Well, let's see.
我要用一下头顶上的投影仪了
I'd like to use the overhead machine here,
多谢
thank you.
首先，我们来整体看一下。这是一个很庞大的东西
First of all, let's look at the whole thing. It's a big story.
它告诉你有某些东西出了问题
Unfortunately, which tells you there is something wrong.
It's at least that big,
#TBD
and it's monolithic.
你不需要现在去理解或看这里的文本
You don't have to understand or look at the text there right now
#TBD
to see that it's monolithic.
它不是Cesaro的实验#TBD
It isn't a thing which is Cesaro's experiment.
它不是从蒙特卡洛过程中抽取出来的
It's not pulled out from the Monte Carlo process.
它不是分离的，让我们来看看为什么
It's not separated. Let's look why.